All right, today's דף Daf is כ"ד, Kaf Daled, and we're here
in Senegal, in the Sessay Dede, and we pick up at the
very bottom of כ"ג עמוד ב', Kaf Gimmel Amud Bet, where it
says the following. We had just had a whole interesting statement of
Reb Yehuda, who was ראש המדברים בכל מקום, Rosh Hamedabrim Bechol Makom,
who had the right to speak first, and then Reb Shimon about
this idea of the sixty עשרונות, Esronot, and how the sizes
of the rabbis, the שיעורים, Shiurim, when they give specific cut-offs and
sizes are, you have to cut off and you have to have
a limit someplace. So now we'll see how the next story does
or does not connect, but now we have another story. It picks
up where it picks up at אמר רב ביבי. Amar Rav Bibi.
It is two lines before the lines get big, the line starts
with the word בו, Bo, and then it's the next word
after. אמר רב ביבי, Amar Rav Bibi, so Rav Bibi said,
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Reb Yehoshua ben Levi, מעשה בפרדה
אחת שמתה, Ma'aseh bepirda achat she-metah, there was a case with a
mule from Rebbi's house, שמתה, she-metah, it died, ושיערו חכמים את דמה
ברביעית. Veshi'aru chachamim et damah berevi'it. And they measured its blood and
they saw that there was a רביעית revi'it of blood. A רביעית
revi'it is the amount, a רביעית revi'it is the same minimum that
we use for a קידוש Kiddush cup, which is about three ounces,
three and a half ounces. Presumably this was a very young mule,
I don't know how, but it only had three ounces of blood.
And the reason that they measured it we will see is because
a dead animal, the carcass of an animal communicates טומאת נבילה, tumat
neveilah, impurity, and the assumption here is that that's true about the
meat of a dead animal, the assumption here is it would be
true about the blood as well, but the way you determine how
much blood is the amount of blood that were it to congeal
would be the same as a כזית, kezayit, the size of an
olive, because the size of an olive is the amount of meat,
of flesh of the animal that communicates impurity. So he measured it
to determine it was a רביעית revi'it because the assumption of the
rabbis is that if
a רביעית revi'it of blood will congeal it will be the size
of an olive and therefore it would communicate impurity. So that's the
story. And now the גמרא Gemara asks on this.
מתיבי רב יצחק בר ביסנא, Metivi Reb Yitzchak bar Bisna, Reb Yitzchak
bar Bisna asked from the following משנה עדיות, Mishnah Eduyot, first wide
line, העיד רבי יהושע ורבי יהושע בן בתירא, He'id Reb Yehoshua ve-Reb
Yehoshua ben Beteira, Reb Yehoshua and Reb Yehoshua ben Beteira gave testimony,
על דם נבילה שהוא טהור, al dam neveilah she-hu tahor, that the
blood of a נבילה, neveilah, of an animal carcass, is pure, doesn't
matter how much you have of it, it's only the meat that
communicates impurity and not the blood. ואמר רבי יהושע בן בתירא, Ve-amar
Reb Yehoshua ben Beteira, and now they're going to even tell a
story that this is because עדיות Eduyot is all about rabbis giving
testimony about previous rulings, previous practices. And so here he's going to
actually give us a testimony about a practice that proves this. מעשה
והיו נוחרים ארדיות לאריות באסטרייא. Ma'aseh vehayu nochrim arudyot le-arayot be-Istraya. So
there was a story where they used to, נוחרים nochrim means to
kill, to slaughter, not through שחיטה, shechitah, and ארדיות arudyot because I
do not have my reference works with me I could not find
out other interpretations, רש"י Rashi here says it just means herds of
animals, but it probably has a more specific meaning than that, for
the lions in the אסטרייא, Istraya, אסטרייא Istraya probably means
the
stadium, של מלך, shel melech, in the king's stadium. This was obviously
the Roman influence in the land of Israel and they had games
with lions and this is what they were doing, slaughtering animals for
the lions. Now how is any of this relevant? Because it says,
והיו עולי רגלים שוקעים עד ארכובותיהם בדם ולא אמרו להם דבר. Vehayu
olei regalim shokim ad arkavoteihem bedam, velo amru lahem davar. And when
people would come up for the
רגל, regel, one of the three major holidays,
they'd be up to
their knees in blood, and nobody ever said, "Hey, you guys are
impure, you gotta go to the מקוה" mikvah or whatever, they came
up in order to go to the Temple. So if this would
have made them impure, somebody would have said something. You wonder also
what were they doing there, apparently they were also somewhat
participating or going if you come up for the רגל regel you
take in some of the culture of the city and they were
watching these games with lions. Anyway, so you see that the blood
of a carcass does not communicate impurity. אישתיק. Ishtik. So he was
silent. He didn't know what to say because he had this testimony,
he had this tradition that they measured the blood of this dead
mule to determine if it was impure, if it would be impure.
אמר ליה רב זריקא, Amar lei Rav Zerika, Rav Zerika said back
to him, מאי טעמא לא קמהדר מר, mai ta'ama lo kamahadar mar,
why didn't you
respond, why didn't you respond to him and tell him, give him
an answer? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to רב
זריקא, Rav Zerika, היכי אהדר ליה, heichi ahadar lei, how should I
respond, how can I respond to him, not even how should I,
how could I be expected to respond? Why? This is a very
interesting גמרא Gemara in the context of everything we learned. you’ve been
experiencing דאמר רבי חנינא, De’amar Rebi Chanina, because Rebbe Chanina interprets the
following verse, which is from the curse in the Torah, the קללה
Klalah in the Torah, and the verse in the end of דברים,
Devarim, and it says והיו חייך תלוים לך מנגד, Ve’hayu chayayecha teluyim
lecha mineged, your life will be suspended, you know, suspended for you
opposite you. So your life will be in suspense, so the your
sense of security over your own life. So how is that interpreted?
זה הלוקח תבואה משנה לשנה. Zeh halokeach tevuah mishanah leshanah. It’s somebody
that has to purchase grain every year. So the way רש״י Rashi
explains it, I might have thought that meant, you know, that meant
a farmer that every year he only has one crop and he
doesn’t know how it’s going to turn out, but רש״י Rashi specifically
notes that it says לוקח, Lokeach, somebody who purchases. So he says
that’s somebody who doesn’t have land. You have land, you have a
sense that you’re going to be able to provide for yourself. You
don’t have land, even if you have enough money this year to
buy up for the whole year, you know, there’s some sense of
you don’t know what next year’s going to bring. So that’s the
first step of the קללה, Klalah, but then the verse goes on
ופחדת לילה ויומם, Ufachadta lailah veyomam, you’ll be afraid day and night.
So that’s not מנגד Mineged is like at a distance. Here, every
night every day you’re afraid. זה הלוקח תבואה מערב שבת לערב שבת.
Zeh halokeach tevuah me’erev Shabbat le’erev Shabbat. That’s somebody that only has
enough money to buy groceries once a week, you know, so he
buys his grain once a week, but every day he’s anxious about
is he going to have money, you know, for next week and
to buy and to buy for next week. ולא תאמין בחייך Velo
ta’amin bechayayecha is the end of the verse, you won’t have even
faith in your own life. So that’s obviously even more radical. זה
הסומך על הפלטר. Zeh hasomech al hapalter. This is somebody that relies
on the on the baker every day for his bread, like maybe
that he gets some, you know, some gift from the baker every
day. So every day he doesn’t even know where his where his
food is coming from. So now how is all of this relevant?
So because here’s what here’s what he said וההוא גברא, Ve’hahu gavra,
so and this person, meaning himself, I’m just trying to remember here
who’s talking right at the top of ק״ד עמוד א׳, Kuf daled
amud aleph, this was
this was רב ביבי. Rav Bibi. So רב ביבי Rav Bibi said,
and that man, meaning himself, על פלטר סמך, Al palter samach, I
rely on the baker every day, so I have absolutely no livelihood,
I’m always anxious about where my next meal is coming from, so
you know, I don’t have the what we would say the ישוב
הדעת, Yishuv hadaas, the presence of mind to actually deal with this
question and give him an appropriate answer. So מאי הוי עלה, Mai
hava alah, so now the גמרא Gemara still wants to know the
resolution. So what was the resolution? We had one version which was
the blood of a carcass causes טומאה, Tumah, another version, another story
with these lions that it does not. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, רבי יהודה מוריינא דבי
נשיא הוה. Rebi Yehuda morayna de’bei nesia hava. Rebbe Yehuda was the
teacher or actually מוריינא Morayna here רש״י Rashi says means he actually
was the הלכה Halacha authority in the house of the נשיא. Nasi.
So in רבי יהודה הנשיא’s Rebi Yehuda Hanasi house or maybe his
children afterwards, you know, they appointed רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda to be
there to be their הלכה Halacha authority in the house of the
of the נשיא. Nasi. ואורי ליה כשמעתיה, Ve’orei leih kishmateih, so he
ruled for רבי, Rebi, remember the first story said רבי, Rebi, they
measured the blood to determine if it was impure. So it wasn’t
really רבי Rebi who was ruling it, it was really based on
רבי יהודה’s Rebi Yehuda ruling. And רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda rules ruled
like רבי Rebi like his own teaching, what’s his teaching, דתנן, Detnan,
we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, רבי יהודה אומר ששה דברים מקולי
בית שמאי ומחומרי בית הלל, Rebi Yehuda omer shishah devarim mikulei Beit
Shammai umichumrei Beit Hillel, there are six things where actually בית שמאי
Beit Shammai is is lenient and בית הלל Beit Hillel is strict,
which is the reverse of what it is usually is. What are
those six things? So one of them is דם נבלה. Dam neveilah.
What about the blood of carcasses? בית שמאי מטהרין, Beit Shammai metaherin,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says this does not communicate טומאה, Tumah, it
has to be only the the flesh, not the blood, ובית הלל
מטמאין Uveit Hillel metame’in and בית הלל Beit Hillel says it does
and we rule like בית הלל Beit Hillel even though they’re more
strict. So basically the answer is is that there’s a debate whether
the blood of a carcass communicates טומאה, Tumah, רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda
says according to בית הלל Beit Hillel it does, so the first
teaching about the blood from a mule was from רבי’s Rebi house,
was רבי יהודה’s Rebi Yehuda ruling for רבי Rebi that it is
a problem and the next story with the blood that was of
these animals that were fed to the lions was a different opinion
that said that it does not communicate טומאה. Tumah. Okay, and now
the גמרא Gemara ends up אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אף כשטימאו
בית הלל, Amar Rebi Yosi Beribi Yehuda af keshetimu Beit Hillel, even
when בית הלל Beit Hillel said it was טמא, Tamei, לא טימאו
אלא ברביעית, Lo timu ela birevi’it, they only said that’s true if
you have a רביעית Revi’it at like three and a half ounces
of blood, הואיל ויכול להקריש ולעמוד על כזית, Ho’il veyachol lehakrish vela’amod
al kezayit, as I said before, because it can congeal and it
will be the size of of an olive, so since that’s the
amount of meat that causes טומאה, Tumah, when blood is causing טומאה
Tumah it’s not causing טומאה Tumah as blood, it’s causing טומאה Tumah
as a type of a pseudo meat. So therefore it only communicate
if in theory you're right, in principle it’s really meat, except blood
is seen as some type of an extension of the category of
meat. But the amount therefore you need is the same way you
would measure the amount of meat, a כזית, Kezayit, so a which
is a solid measure. So therefore the measure of a רביעית, Revi’it,
which is a liquid measure, is the amount of blood that were
to congeal would be of the size. Now what is this doing
in our entire discussion? So רש״י Rashi says because we had a
whole discussion yesterday at the end of yesterday about like you know,
the the שיעורים, Shiurim, like the measurements of the rabbis and you
know, exactly this much for this, exactly that much for that. So
here you see there’s a whole little issue about the measure and
how do you measure blood standard for meat and so on. תוספות
Tosafot says it’s because we mentioned yesterday that רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda
is
ראש המדברים בכל מקום. Rosh hamedabrim bechol makom. was
also appointed to
be the
פוסק *posek* in רבי יהודה הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi*'s house so he
thinks that maybe there's some connection you know because of his status
that that's also the role that he played in רבי יהודה הנשיא
*Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi*'s house. Okay and now we look at the next
משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. אין ein מתנדבים לוג log שנים וחמשה אבל מתנדבים
שלשה וארבעה וששה ומששה ולמעלה *Ein mitnadvim log shnayim vachamisha aval mitnadvim
shlosha vearba veshisha umishisha ulemala*. Now the the
we're going to see that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will learn it
out from a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* but what you have is something
called מנחת נסכים nesachim, *minchas nesachim* which means which actually I think
we just read in this last week's פרשה *parsha*. We did. So
which is after a after an
any any freewill animals animal sacrifice meaning an עולה olah. *olah* or
a שלמים *shelamim* as opposed to a sin offering you always bring
with it a מנחה minchah *mincha* which is a mixture of flour
and oil different amounts of flour and oil based on the animal
and wine and different amounts of wine based on the animal. So
the the משנה mishnah. *mishnah* here assumes that you can bring the
wine as a separate gift as a separate offering even when it's
not coming together with the animal. But they assume that it's based
on this model of the wine that came with the animals so
it has to be the same if you would denominations. So how
much wine do you bring with the animals? So basically if you
know we say this in the מוסף *Musaf* חצי ההין לפר *chatzi
hahin lapar* שלישית ההין לאיל le'ayil *shelishis hahin laayil* רביעית ההין לכבש
lekeves, יין *reviis hahin lakeves yayin*. So a הין *hin* is twelve
לוג log. *log*. Again a לוג log, *log* a לוג log? *log*
is about twelve ounces. So a הין *hin* is twelve of those.
So half of that six would be six לוג log *log* for
a פר *par* for a cow a third would be four right
a third of twelve is four four לוג log *log* for a
ram and three a quarter of twelve is three three לוג log
*log* for a sheep. So if you can give the wine offering
by itself but it has to be some you know using those
denominations of three four and six. So if three you need denominations
of three four and six one is out two is out right?
Now
five is out right? Because three and four but but you have
three you have four you have six. Can you make seven out
of three four and six? Yes. Can you make eight? Yeah two
fours. Right? Can you make nine? Yes six and three. So you
do the math after six you can make any any number. Okay
so that's what this משנה mishnah. *mishnah* teaches. So let's take a
look. I do apologize for the heat not my fault though. I
know. אין ein מתנדבים לוג log שנים *Ein mitnadvim log shnayim*—one speaker
move it further out—oh okay you can't give two לוג log. *log*
וחמשה *vachamisha* and you can't give five אבל מתנדבים שלשה וארבעה וששה
*aval mitnadvim shlosha vearba veshisha* three four and six that's the amount
that was brought with the animals ומששה ולמעלה *umishisha ulemala* and from
six above because all any number more than six could be made
with those denominations. Okay so let's look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
איבעיא להו *Ibaya lehu* they raised the question יש קבע keva לנסכים
lenesachim. או אין קבע לנסכים *yesh keva lanesachim o ein keva lanesachim*.
So when if I give I say I'm going to give five
לוג log. *log* of wine as a sacrifice. By the way what
would they do with it? They don't burn you don't burn wine
you don't throw it on the מזבח *mizbe’ach*. Well what did they
do with the wine that came with the animals? They poured it
in one of the corners on the top of the altar they
had actually a funnel and you poured the wine down the funnel
and actually fell into poured into a cavity inside of the altar.
It was a huge altar. So if you donate the wine then
it would also do the same you would pour it down the
funnel. What?
It's like a pot. Like a it's a fraternity I was just—okay
anyway.
Are you are you in it? So here's the question. Let's say
you say let's say you say I'm going to give six לוג
log, *log* of wine which the משנה mishnah *mishnah* said you can.
Do you have to give it as a unit of six לוג
*log* or can you break it up? Okay that's the question יש
קבע לנסכים או אין קבע *yesh keva lanesachim o ein keva*. When
you say a certain amount does it have to be given all
together or not as a unit? So let's see what who cares.
איבעיא להו *Ibaya lehu* יש קבע לנסכים או אין קבע לנסכים *yesh
keva lanesachim o ein keva lanesachim* is there fixed or not fixed?
היכי דמי *Heichi dami* what's the case? כגון דאייתי חמשה *Kegon deaisei
chamisha* you brought five which the משנה Mishna *mishnah* said you're not
able to do. So but okay but I now sanctified these five
לוג *log* of wine what do I do with it? So אי
אמרת אין קבע לנסכים *ei amart ein keva lanesachim* you're not fixed
to bring it all as one unit משיך ומקריב ארבעה arba'ah מינייהו
*mashich umakriv arba minayhu* take out four of the לוג *log* because
four is an acceptable unit דחזי לאיל *dechazi laayil*
that's the amount of wine you would bring with a ram ואידך
*veidach* then you're left with one לוג *log* left over so הוי
נדבה *havei nidava* that would be just a gift. Now what does
it mean a gift? Doesn't mean to put on the altar but
you'll give it to the next guy who needs an extra לוג
*log* of wine and he'll bring it with his sacrifice. Okay so
if you're not fixed with that as a unit so if you
brought the wrong number five you could still bring part of it
and the the other one you'd give away. And what if it
was a unit? If it was a unit ואי אמרת יש קבע
לנסכים *veei amart yesh keva lanesachim* if you had to bring the
five as a unit עד דממלי להו לא lo קרבי *ad demamlei
lehu lo karvei* so you can't go any less than five you're
stuck with this as a unit you'd have to get it up
to six you'd have to bring another לוג *log* and then you
could bring all six. Because then you're still keeping the five all
together. מאי? mai
So what's the story? אמר אביי Amar Abaye תא שמע ta shma
come and hear. ששה לנדבה shisha lenedava with the— there were,
in the Temple, there were 13 essentially צדקה tzedakah boxes. But they
weren't for הצלה Hatzalah or anything like— or חב"ד. Chabad. There were
13 צדקה tzedakah boxes for all different types of ways in which
people would put money for sacrifices. Now the way it would work
is the following is you had a— you had some money, for
example leftover money, you sanctified a pile of money for a sacrifice,
you used most of it to buy— you had left over. What
do you do with it? So there's a lot of different types
of scenarios where you could have leftover money and you would put
it in these various boxes and then they would draw on those
funds when it was a slow day in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash and it's— it doesn't look nice if nothing's happening and it
looks like people are ignoring the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if
it was a slow day, they would draw on those funds and
they would
bring עולות, olot, they'd bring burnt offerings to keep things going, you
know, make it, you know, still make it look like— like business—
like it was a busy day. So there were six— so here's
what the משנה Mishna teaches. Six of those boxes, ששה לנדבה, shisha
lenedava, there were six that were for the free will offerings, meaning
for to draw on to use for— for these— for the burnt
offerings when the— when the altar was right— was not busy. וכנגד
מי? v'keneged mi? Why did you need six? What do they represent?
כנגד keneged and here are six ways that people will have leftover
money from sacrifices that— that the rabbis sort of saw as conceptually
distinct categories. So מותר חטאת, mostar chatat, money leftover from money I'd
sanctified for a sin offering. ומותר אשם, umostar asham, money leftover from
that I'd sanctified for an אשם, asham, which is similar but it's
a guilt offering, not a sin offering. We won't go into details
now of the differences. ומותר אשם נזיר, umostar asham nazir, a specific
type of אשם asham is the אשם asham that a נזיר nazir
brings to end his נזירות nezirut period. So that's different, that's not
about actual sin, that's just a way to end his נזירות nezirut
period. So if he had leftover money from money that was sanctified
for that purpose. Or ומותר אשם מצורע, umostar asham metzora, leftover money
for an— for the אשם asham of a מצורע, metzora, somebody who
was, you know, had spots and what we would call leprous and
was טמא, tamei, he would have to— when he went through a
purification process, he would end that process by bringing an אשם. asham.
So if he does sanctified money and there was leftover money, he
would put it in this box. ומותר קינים, umostar kinim, money leftover
from bird sacrifices. ומותר מנחת חוטא, umostar minchat chote, and money leftover
from a sin offering sacrifice— oh, I hope he has the— the
thing.
You have the thing? Oh, thank you. Okay, so—
okay, ומותר מנחת חוטא, mostar minchat chote, so— so
money
leftover from— alright, from a מנחה minchah that was— sometimes a מנחה
mincha can be brought as a certain type of a sin offering.
So if you have money leftover from that, you would also put
it in this box. Now the— if you'll notice the common denominator
about all of these things is is that they were obligatory sacrifices.
And that's really where, you know, if you have an obligatory sacrifice
and you've used up the money, this money has been designated for
an obligation and for a specific type of obligatory
sacrifice— way too many distractions right now, bit too much heat. Alright,
so— alright, I'm not dressed for it, I forgot. Anyway, so— so
if there— so if money is designated for these obligatory— what? Yeah,
take a picture of that there. We're going to put it on
my website.
Everybody smile. No, we should be looking in the גמרא. Gemara Yeah,
in action. Alright, in action. So money leftover for these sacrifices— Russo
is still smiling. Russo's prone to doing that. I know.
Okay, he's a camera hog. Okay, so anyway in— okay, thank you.
So money leftover for all of these
things— alright, are we done? Almost, I'm
sorry. Alright, it's my fault, I asked you to do it. Okay,
anyway, okay.
I see. Okay. Alright, so anyway, all of these things are obligatory
sacrifices. You sanctified money for them, you had it leftover, what are
you supposed to do with it? So you can't use it for
the obligation, you don't have the obligation anymore, you used most of
the money for the obligation. So the leftover money, as I said,
gets— because gets— gets dedicated to the Temple or given to this
Temple fund which gets drawn on to bring the sin offerings when
there is— when it's a slow day. Okay, so anyway let's see
how— what the גמרא's Gemara question is about all of this. So
it says like this: ואי איתא, v'ei ita, if it's true that
if you had leftover—
if you had a— if you could only bring, if you...
Okay.
I gotta regain my focus. Sorry. It's my— well, it's my fault.
Okay, sorry. Alright. Let's all take a minute to cool off and
get— and just regain my focus. Alright. Water? No,
I'm
okay. Alright.
So anyway, these were all different ways in which... So anyway, these
were all different ways in which people would donate money that would
then be used for an עולה. So the גמרא Gemara set a
scenario: you have you brought these five לוג of wine.
Now one possibility is you can't break it up, you have to
wait to the six לוג. Fine, you'll bring it all. But the
other possibility is you can break it up, you bring four and
you have one left over. So right now the גמרא's Gemara assuming
if you have left over, it's like you have left over by
any other type of thing. What do you do with left over
funds you that you have? You give it, put it into one
of these boxes and this is used for this type of a
way of keeping the altar running. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara so
the גמרא's Gemara saying is, and we see that they've categorized it
based on different ways in which money is left over. So why
didn't they have a box for this? Okay, so that's the question.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואי איתא, ve'ei issa, if
you really would have this scenario, לישקין lishkin שופר shofar אחרינא achrina
כנגד kineged מותר motar נסכים, nesachim. have another שופר shofar like, you
know, but another box essentially for the left over of the oil
of the wine sacrifices. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הנך hanach
לנדבת ציבור linidvas tzibur אזלי. azli. So הני hani שכיחי. shechichi. So
all those other things you're going to use the money to buy,
as I said, communal sacrifices when the altar is not busy. הני
hani שכיחי, shechichi, but here left over wine, it's very it's very
common how I can make use of left over wine. How can
I make use of left over wine? אפשר efshar דמצטרפי demitztrarpi דמר
demar ודמר udemar בהדי הדדי, bahadi hadadi, that I can get, you
know, I can get together with somebody else who, you know, also
didn't bring enough wine. Or every every sacrifice, almost every sacrifice comes
with flour and wine, you know, flour and oil and wine. So
if I have a little left over, I'll give it to you,
you have a little less than you need and it'll automatically be
put to use. So you're not going to need to trans you
know to transfer it into funds and put the funds in this
box, as opposed to all these other cases you had no option
of what to do with the money. Okay, so that's how we
answer that. וקרבי, vekarvi, then it would be offered. אמר רבא, amar
Rava, so now we're still trying to figure out if you can
break up that unit or not. תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear, אזרח. ezrach. So this is in the verses about bringing the
נסכים. nesachim. This is where we're going to learn that you can
bring it as a separate sacrifice. So here it said every citizen,
again there's that word from last night, every citizen should do this,
should bring the flour and oil together with the wine with the
animal sacrifices. So what does that word teach you? מלמד melamed שמתנדבין
shemisnadvin נסכים.
That somehow that word אזרח ezrach is always seen as a little
unusual, because it is unusual as you know in the text it's
not so common. And that's to tell you like it broadens the
scope. How does it broaden the scope? That you can bring the
wine sacrifices by themselves. You can give a free will wine sacrifice
even when it's not coming together with the animal sacrifice. וכמה? vekama?
שלושה shlosha לוגין. login. And how much can you give minimum? Three
לוג, because that's the minimum that would come with an animal sacrifice.
ומניין uminiyan שאם she'im רוצה rotze להוסיף lehosef יוסיף? yosef? How do
I know if you want to have more than three you can?
תלמוד לומר talmud lomar יהיה, yihye, another word in the verse is
shall be, which is again seen as a broadening the scope. יכול
yachol יפחות? yifchos? Maybe you can have less than the three than
three לוג? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ככה. kacha. No, it has to
be this way. So from there we learn out all of the
principles of our משנה. Somehow from the word אזרח, ezrach, I don't
know exactly how, we learn out that you can do this independent
of the animal sacrifice. And from various words we learn out it
can't it has to be based on the denominations. So it can't
be less than the way it existed with the animals, but you
can add units together and make larger unit. Okay, so now מאי
mai, יוסיף? yosef? So the גמרא Gemara says what does this mean
that you can add? אילימא eileima ארבעה arba'ah ושישה, veshisha, if it's
to tell me that you can have the other units that we
find by the other animals, four לוג and six לוג which we
find by a ram and by a cow. מאי שנא mai shna
שלושה shlosha דחזו dechazu לכבש, ארבעה ושישה veshisha נמי nami חזו chazu
לאיל ופר? ufar? I wouldn't need a special פסוק to tell me
that, because I already start by telling me I can bring the
standard units. So the same way I know I can bring three
because that's the amount that comes with a sheep, I know I
can bring a I know I can bring four and six because
that's the amount that comes with a ram and a cow. So
when it says how do I know I can bring more, I
don't need it to tell me four and six. So three, four
and six are all the same principle, you can bring the standard
units. So what does more mean? אלא ela לאו, lav, what does
more mean? More means in a way that's not the standard units.
חמישה, chamisha, it must mean that I can bring five. Now how
could I bring five? ושמע מינה ushma mina אין קבע לנסכים. The
only way I could bring five is if I bring five and
then I do of those five I bring four and I use
the one for some other purpose.
So the גמרא Gemara so the גמרא Gemara actually thinks that this
is a good answer. You didn't hear the announcement?
No? Ah, sorry. So שמע מינה, shma mina, that is a good
proof. Now it doesn't seem to be such a good proof to
me, because why would we be teaching that you can bring five
if you can't bring it as a whole unit and then you
would have to subdivide it and not even bring all of it
at once. But some reason because it says how do I know
I can do things that are not even these exact units and
to do more, from that the גמרא Gemara thinks that the point
is that you can bring five and even though you can't offer
it all up at once, you take four out of it and
then you use the one for something else. But the גמרא's Gemara
not done. אמר amar רב אשי, Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav
Ashi says ואנן va'anan לא תנן tnan הכי. hachi. We didn't teach
at our משנה. Our משנה says you can't bring five. So אין
מתנדבין misnadvin לוג שניים shnayim וחמישה, vachamisha, you cannot bring two לוג
or five לוג. So קתני חמשה דומיא דשנים, ktani chamisha dumya d'shnaim,
so the implication is the problem with five is equivalent to the
problem of two. מה שנים דלא חזו כלל, Ma shnaim d'lo chazu
klal, the same way when you bring two, there's no way you
can put two on the altar, because you haven't hit the minimum
of three. אף חמשה נמי דלא חזו כלל, af chamisha nami d'lo
chazu klal, so five would mean there's no way you can put
any part of it on the altar, you have to wait till
you get to six. So, so comparing five and two makes it
sound like you can't offer up five at all until you get
to six. So גמרא Gemara says מידי איריא midi irya what is
that a proof? הכי איתא והכי איתא, hachi deesa v'hachi deesa, each
one is according to its own, you know, its own category, its
own rules. So two and five you can't bring, but there're different
implications. Two you wouldn't be able to bring it all, and if
you brought five, then we won't use the whole five but maybe
we could use four out of the five. All right, so now
the גמרא's Gemara going to, it still hasn't resolved it. אמר אביי
Amar Abaye so here's אביי Abaye is going to ask a question.
אם תמצא לומר אין קבע לנסכים, Im timtzo lomar ein kevah l'nisachim,
if you say there's no fixed amount which means that
if you bring a unit you can break it up into different,
different quantities, הא אין קבע לנסכים ha ein kevah l'nisachim so fine
then I then there is no fixed, then it doesn't the amount
doesn't get fixed and I don't have any questions to ask. But
אם תמצא לומר יש קבע לנסכים im timtzo lomar yesh kevah l'nisachim
if you do say that when you bring an amount it's fixed
and you can't now take a smaller part out of it, you
can only add to it, here's my question. עד עשרה פשיטא לי,
Ad asara pshita li, if anybody makes a vow of any unit
up to ten, then it's obvious to me that you can bring
it because if he said any because seven, remember the units we
have in the תורה Torah of wine are three, four and six
לוג. So if somebody said seven, that would be three and four.
If somebody said eight, that would be four and four. If somebody
said nine, that would be six and three but there is no
five, that would be six and three. If somebody said ten, that
would be six and four. Okay so all of those I understand
are any obvious combination of two units. What happens if somebody says
eleven? חד עשר מיבעיא לי Chad asar miba'ei li now how can
you get eleven out of, out of three, four and six? Four,
four and three. Four, four and three. But that's like a weird
combination, it's not just two, it's like two of one and one
of another, there's like no symmetry to that. Okay, so that's, so
we could say when you said eleven, when you brought eleven, I'm
serious, you meant eleven and and you meant four four and three,
or we could say probably, you know, you meant to bring twelve
because that's like, that's a more easy combination of two sixes, and
therefore you would need to wait till you add another one to
your eleven to offer it up. So that's his question. מאי, what
do we say? גברא לשני פרים קמיכוין Gavra l'shnei parim kam m'khavein
although you brought eleven and in your mind you were really thinking
of the amount of two sixes, for six is what you would
bring for a cow, two cows, ועד דמלא להו לא קרבי v'ad
d'mamale leihu lo kariv and until you get it up to twelve
you can't offer it. או דילמא לשני אילים וכבש אחד קמיכוין O
dilma l'shnei eilim v'keves echad kam m'khavein or do we mean two
rams, a ram is four, okay, because that's how much לוג, and
one and one, where were we and one and one sheep which
is three. Okay so תרי מחד מינא וחד מחד מינא אמרינן או
לא
מאי. trei mikhada mina v'chad mikhada mina amrinan o lo mai.
So do we say two of one type and one of another,
would we say that that's what you meant or not, or that's
like, that's not elegant, it's not symmetrical, we're going to, it's hard
to assume you meant that. So גמרא Gemara says תיקו teiku we
leave it unanswered. Okay, so that was a cute little question, of
course the משנה sounds like you can bring any unit over six,
so it sounds like that we would interpret it that way. But,
but that's a question that's unanswered, that if you can only bring
these units what happens when, what happens if you bring the five
which does that, are you stuck at five or can you then
take off part of it? Let's finish up and we are now
going to finish the
פרק. perek. מתנדבין יין ואין מתנדבין שמן דברי רבי עקיבא. Mitnadvin yayin
v'ein mitnadvin shemen, divrei Rabbi Akiva. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says,
so remember what came with the animals was a mixture of flour
and oil which came with every animal and a separate thing of
wine. So we have said you can bring the wine by itself,
you can just offer up a wine sacrifice, certainly quite bizarre. You
read the entire תורה Torah you would never have thought that. It
just speaks about animal sacrifices, מנחה mincha sacrifices, but the rabbis actually
find a way to find other, other ways of reading that it's
possible to bring even other types of things, you know, which I
think is very powerful because you can imagine somebody that let's say
is a, you know, grows grapes for a living and would maybe
want to just give a wine sacrifice and you know, although you
could buy other types of things but you know, there could be
a certain power to that. So that's what we say, that you
bring wine. Now the question is, okay, but what else came with
the animal? Flour and oil mixed together, now flour and oil is
a מנחה mincha. we know you can give a מנחה. Mincha What
about can you give just one of those ingredients? Can you give
just שמן shemen or just flour? So that's the question that the
משנה now asks. So let's take a look. מתנדבין יין ואין מתנדבין
שמן, Mitnadvin yayin v'ein mitnadvin shemen, you can give a gift like
a free will sacrifice of, of wine but not of oil, דברי
רבי עקיבא divrei Rabbi Akiva that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says.
רבי טרפון אומר Rabbi Tarfon omer רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says מתנדבין
שמן, mitnadvin shemen,
no you can give oil. אמר רבי טרפון Amar Rabbi Tarfon so
here's his argument. מה מצינו ביין שהוא בא בחובה ובא בנדבה Ma
matzinu b'yayin shehu ba b'chova uva b'nedava wine comes as an obligation
when you bring an animal sacrifice and it can come by itself
as a free
will sacrifice אף שמן af shemen oil
by itself. אמר לו Amar lo, רבי עקיבא *Amar lo Rabbi Akiva*,
Rabbi Akiva said back to him, לא *Lo*, no, that's not a
comparison. אם אמרת ביין שכן קרב עם חובתו בפני עצמו *Im amarta
b'yayin sheken karev im chovaso bifnei atzmo*, wine is brought with its
obligation, with the animal sacrifice, but it's brought by itself. You have
a separate, you know, thing of wine. It's brought as a unit
of wine. So that's why you can also give it by itself.
תאמר בשמן *Tomar b'shemen*, will you say that by oil, שאינו קרב
עם חובתו בפני עצמו *she'eino karev im chovaso bifnei atzmo*, even when
you bring it with its obligation, you don't bring just oil. You
bring an oil-flour mixture. So there's no model of bringing just oil.
There's a model of bringing just wine, but there's no model of
bringing just oil. So that's the end of that debate. Then the
משנה *Mishna* ends up the פרק *perek* saying the following: אין שנים
מתנדבין עישרון אחד *Ein shnayim misnadvin isaron echad*. Here's a question: can
you go into partnership? Can you say 'I don't have enough money
for this sacrifice, I want to give a free will sacrifice,' not
an obligatory, obligatory has to be just your own except for קרבן
פסח *Korban Pesach*. But if it's a free will sacrifice, I'd like
to bring that. You know, it's פסח *Pesach* or it's סוכות *Succos*,
we're all going up to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, I'd like to bring a
sheep sacrifice, but I don't have enough money. Would you split it
with me? You're allowed to do that. You're allowed to go into
partnership for any sacrifice, any animal sacrifice and even birds, but not
for a מנחה Mincha *mincha*. And we will see why in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So let's read that. אין שנים מתנדבין עישרון אחד
*Ein shnayim misnadvin isaron echad*. Two people cannot go into partnership, like,
you know, jointly give one עישרון *isaron*, one מנחה Mincha *mincha*, which
is the smallest amount. אבל מתנדבין עולה ושלמים *Aval misnadvin olah u'shlamim*.
They can jointly give a free will burnt offering or a שלמים
*shlamim* peace offering. ועוף *V'of*, and they can even give a free
will bird sacrifice as an עולה *olah* or as an עולה *olah*.
אפילו פרידה אחת *Afilyu prida achas*, even if it's just one bird.
Normally birds come as two birds usually in the תורה *Torah*, but
even one bird. Any animal sacrifice, even if it's small, you can
go in jointly, but not with a מנחה Mincha *mincha*. Okay, and
we'll see why in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So first we have
to refer to the רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי טרפון *Rabbi
Tarfon* debate. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, מדברי שניהם *midivrei shneihem*, from both
their positions about the oil, נלמוד *nilmod*, we can infer, מתנדב אדם
מנחת נסכים בכל יום *misnadev adam minchas nesachim b'chol yom*, that you
can actually give, they're just debating: can you give the oil by
itself? But presumably and רבי עקיבא's *Rabbi Akiva's* point is well because
it never comes by itself. So implicitly רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would
agree that you can donate, you know, give as a sacrifice, the
oil mixed with the flour, which is מנחת נסכים *minchas nesachim*. Now
of course you'll say well of course that's a מנחה Mincha *mincha*,
we know you can give a מנחה Mincha *mincha*. No, but it's
different because the מנחה Mincha *mincha* in the תורה *Torah*, the ratio
of flour to oil is different and therefore what this is telling
you is is that there's like a new type of a מנחה
Mincha. *mincha* you can give even as a free will sacrifice, not
just the מנחות *minchos* that the תורה *Torah* lists which have a
certain ratio of flour and oil, but even the ones that come
with the animal sacrifices because that would be just like the wine.
Okay. פשיטא *Pshita*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that's obvious. מהו דתימא
*Mahu d'seima*, מנחת נדבה גלי בה רחמנא *minchas nedavah gali bei rachmana*,
maybe I would say that when it comes to a מנחה Mincha,
*mincha* the תורה *Torah* made it very clear. הני חמשה מנחות אין
*Hanei chamisha menachos in*, the five types of מנחות *menachos* prepared different
ways that are listed in ויקרא *Vayikra*, those are the only types
of מנחות *menachos* that you can give by themselves. טפי לא *Tfei
lo*, maybe no more. So wine, the תורה *Torah* never spoke about,
so I'll say wine you can give by itself. But מנחה Mincha.
*mincha*, maybe it's just the list that exists and no more than
that list. קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan*, so this teaches us,
הני מילי בסתמא *hanei mili b'stama*. That's if you're not explicit, we
assume you meant a מנחה *mincha* from that list of the five
in the תורה *Torah*. אבל היכא דפריש פריש *Aval heicha d'parish parish*,
if you're explicit and you say 'I want to give a מנחה
*mincha* like the מנחה *mincha* that comes with animals' where again it's
a different ratio of flour to oil, you can give that type
of a מנחה *mincha*. Now we end off this פרק *perek* with
I think a very lovely, a very lovely, more sort of philosophical
and agadic discussion. So let's take a look, or religious discussion. אין
שנים מתנדבין *Ein shnayim misnadvin*, two people cannot go into partnership by
an animal sacrifice, by a מנחה *mincha*. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*, what's
the reason? אילימא משום דכתיב *Ilima mishum d'ksiv*, if it's because when
it speaks about a מנחה *mincha* it says תקריב *takriv*, you shall
bring in the singular, so singular means only an individual can bring
not in partnership. עולה נמי הא כתיב *Olah nami ha ksiv*, by
עולה *olah* it also says יקריב *yakriv*, that you shall bring an
עולה *olah* and the singular. אלא עולה מאי טעמא *Ela olah mai
ta'ama*, why do I know an עולה *olah* you can be in
partnership? דכתיב *D'ksiv*, because another verse says לעולותיכם *l'oloseichem*, for your plural
עולות *olos*. So that indicates the idea that maybe it can be
even with multiple people, even in partnership. So if that's the issue,
מנחה נמי הא כתיב *mincha nami ha ksiv*, we have a similar
verse by the מנחה *mincha*, למנחותיכם *l'minchoseichem*, your plural מנחות *menachos*. So
again it's in the plural. So there's nothing different between the way
it talks about מנחה *mincha* and the way it talks about an
עולה *olah*. So if you can go into partnership with one, why
not the other? אלא משום דכתיב ביה נפש nefesh *Ela mishum d'ksiv
bei nefesh*, because it says a soul. And if you read the
beginning of the ויקרא *Vayikra* it says אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן
*Adam ki yakriv mikem korban*, if a person brings a קרבן *korban*
and it talks about animal sacrifices. And then when it gets to
the מנחה *mincha* it says ונפש כי תקריב *V'nefesh ki takriv*, and
if a soul brings a מנחה *mincha*. So it switched. So the
soul, so here it's learning out from the idea of soul as
opposed to a person means like a single person, you know, when
a soul... who has that sense of, you know, maybe the uniqueness
of the soul, and it's very much focused on an individual. So
it's only one person and not two. So now right now we
know it from a verse but we have not explained any logic
for it. So the גמרא now is going to focus on the
word soul that it uses by מנחה to make another דרשה Drasha
and although the גמרא doesn't suggest that they're connected, I would like
to think that they are. So let's see what the דרשה Drasha
is that the גמרא says. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, first
it says we taught similarly in a ברייתא. Baraita. רבי אומר Rebbi
omer אשר יקריב קרבנו לכל נדריהם ולכל נדבתם אשר יקריבו להשם asher
yakriv korbano lechol nidreihem ulechol nidvosam asher yakrivu la'Hashem that he will
bring his sacrifice, singular, for all of their, you know, vows and
oaths that they will bring to God. So it starts in the
singular and it shifts to the plural. What does that tell you?
הכל באים בשותפות. Hakol ba'im beshutfus. All sacrifices can come in, you
know, in partnership with multiple people donating it, at least free will
sacrifices. לא סילקה הכתוב Lo silleka hakatuv the Torah only removed אלא
מנחה, ella Mincha, the מנחה שנאמר נפש, shenne'emar nefesh, it uses the
word soul to mean it can only come from a single person.
אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, so now רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
makes his דרשה. Drasha. מפני מה נשתנית מנחה? Mipnei ma nishnis Mincha?
Why is מנחה changed in the verse שנאמר בה נפש? shenne'emar bah
nefesh? Why does מנחה use the word נפש in the גמרא in
the Torah? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, God is
saying, מי דרכו להביא מנחה? mi darko lehavi Mincha? Who is which
type of a person brings a מנחה sacrifice rather than an animal
sacrifice? So the answer is obvious, עני, ani, a poor person who
can't afford an animal sacrifice. So מעלה אני עליו כאילו הקריב נפשו
לפני. ma'ale ani alav ke'illu hikriv nafsho lefanai. It's I treat it
as if you've offered up your very soul. So even though, you
know, for you this is the most important thing that you can
give and what you're able to give and therefore what for a
rich person, you know, sometimes for a rich person the animal sacrifice
doesn't even mean anything, he has so much money, but for you
this means a tremendous amount and it's just as important as what
it is for the rich person. This is actually one of the
places the גמרא I think in another context says that here the
principle of אחד הממעיט ואחד המרבה ובלבד שיכוון לבו לשמים. echad hamamit
ve'echad hamarbeh uvelvad sheyachavein libo lashamayim. It doesn't matter whether you do
a lot or a little, what matters is that your heart is
to heaven. Okay and let's see how the גמרא ends this. אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מה נשתנית מנחה שנאמר בה חמשה מיני
טיגון הללו? ma nishnis Mincha shenne'emar bo chamishah minei tigun hallalu? In
what way is the מנחה why by מנחה does the Torah give
five different ways of preparing it? You either fry it or you
deep fry it or you bake it. It's all these different ways.
Why is it bizarre, right? You know, it's just flour and oil.
Who cares how you prepare? משל למלך בשר ודם, mashal lemelech basar
vadam, I mean, שעשו לו אוהבו סעודה. she'asu lo ohavo seuda. That's
say
there's a king that somebody very close to him made for him
a meal. ויודע בו שהוא עני, Veyode'a bo shehu ani, but he
knew this person is poor, he's not going to be able to
give him all these delicacies. So what does the king say? אמר
לו, so he says to him, עשה לי מן חמשה מיני טיגון
כדי שאהנה ממך. asei li min chamishah minei tigun kedei she'ehaneh mimmecha.
Says, you know what, I would love it if you would make
me all those different types of pastries and, you know, all those
different types of delicacies, you know, delicious things that you can do
with flour and oil. So it's in a way, it's, you know,
I think the point being it's not like the king needs it
but that this is the way that it gives the person the
opportunity to feel that he is, you know, showing his love for
the king and his respect for the king by doing everything he's
able to do within his context and doing it in a very
fancy way. So again playing about the power about what that means
for the poor person to be giving it from him, you know,
and to be seeing how from that perspective or, you know, it's
not the objective question about how much money is spent. The question
about the way in which it's given and what that sacrifice means
and what that gift means. So I'd like to think that that's
also why
and maybe this is just speculation, that's also why you can't go
don't go in partnership with a מנחה. Because, you know, because if
there's this sense like
I'm seeing if I can articulate this, but I think that the
idea is that it's almost like insulting. You know, you're giving me
this option to bring something that's this flour and oil and, you
know, it's very very meaningful to me and if I'm, you know,
if basically I'm making a statement that I can't I'm trying to
think how to say this. It's not I don't mean it's like
insulting to God. I mean it's insulting like to the עני, ani,
which is, you know what, it's okay, you can even give a
half of מנחה, you can even give a third of a מנחה.
It's like then then it feels very much like it's, you know,
you're just doing it to make me feel good, it doesn't mean
anything. Right? Because partnership doesn't just say two, partnership could be twenty.
Somebody my cousin once told me that he was in Israel many
years ago where, you know, and in one of these שטיבל shtiebel
שולס shuls every time anybody got an עליה, aliya, you know, and
they made a מי שבירך, mi shebeirach, it says יתן מתנה לבית
הכנסת, yitein matana leveish haknesses, you know, מתנה matana מתנה matana nobody
would ever give an amount, right? So you just say מתנה. matana.
So a gift. So they put up a little sign which basically
said אין מתנה פחות מחמשה שקלים, ein matana pachos mechamesh shekalim,
right? So מתנה matana minimum מתנה matana is five shekels. So a
guy gets an עליה aliya and he says חצי מתנה. chatzi matana.
So half a מתנה. matana.
So I think that that's maybe the point like, you know, that
that if you allow me to go to partnership then you're even
saying like okay do whatever you want it doesn't matter. So no,
this is actually something of significance. And it might take time to
be able to afford it, but when you give it, you've really
done something very meaningful. I also wanted to say something about the
חמשת מיני תיקון chamishas minei tikkun which I think maybe ties into
that, which is I still remember when I just got married that
we got, you know, a wedding gift from somebody who had really
had no money from the community and it was like, you know,
it was like a set of like plastic kitchen implements, like, you
know, a ladle or something like that, you know, maybe cost like
five ten dollars. I did not need this, you know, she needed
her money much more than I, you know, I needed this gift.
So I felt very guilty about it and, you know, my wife's
grandfather who passed away recently was a very wise man, and he
said, you know, he said, you know, it it's so much important
to her that she be able to give you a gift. You
know, what does it mean to be, you know, a poor person
who feels like you're not an, you know, you're not an active
member of society and you're not you're not able to reciprocate and,
you know, you're not able to contribute. So to say, oh you're
so poor that you can only receive and you can't give, you
know, really undermines a person's dignity and sense of self-worth. So I
think that that's like part of what's going on here, you know,
is that the different ways in which you can give and feel
like you're really doing something of significance and of meaning. And again,
I think that that is something to do with why it can't
be subdivided. So maybe we will end. יישר כח. shkoiach. יישר כח.
shkoiach.